- [Mike] So our first step is to create an Elixir
project and get some code running.
- [Nicole] And no surprise, Elixir has
conventions for organizing projects and
great tooling to automate project tasks.
- To create a new Elixir project, we use
the mix command and we say mix new,
and then the name of our project is going to be servy.
And it generated a few files and directories there.
We'll look at those in just a minute.
Now the mix tool lets us automate common project tasks.
In fact, if you just want to see all the tasks,
you do mix help and it lists all those out.
So we did the mix new to create a new Elixir project,
but there's a load of tasks in here for just common
things you want to do around your Elixir project.
So I'm just going to change directory into that servy
project directory and then open it up in my editor.
Let's take a quick peek at the lightweight directory
structure that the mix new command created.
We've got a lib directory, this is where
our application code's going to live,
and it generated a servy.ex file,
which we'll look at in just a second.
We also have a test directory, which no
surprise has some tests inside of those,
some generated tests.
Again, we'll look at those a little bit later.
And then we have this mix.exs and this is where
we configure our project and its dependencies.
We'll have to add a dependency a little bit later on in
the course, so we'll come back to this file as well.
- Now don't let the two file
extensions .ex and .exs throw you.
Both types of files contain Elixir code.
.ex files are meant to be compiled and then run,
whereas .exs files are effectively interpreted
like scripts thus the trailing S.
Most of the time though,
you'll just use the .ex extension
- And that's exactly the extension we have on this
servy.ex because it's application code and all of our
application code is going to have a .ex extension.
So I'm just going to remove these
comments so we can focus on the code.
And Elixir code is always organized in named modules.
So the file starts by defining a module here,
which is just a namespace for functions.
It uses defmodule, then the
name of the module is Servy.
Notice that it starts with an uppercase character
and all module names in Elixir use camel case.
Then inside of the module, we have a named
function called hello and the function
names are lowercase with underscores or snake case.
And all named functions must be
defined inside of a module.
- But one thing that might trip you up that at least it
tripped me up was trying to remember to type the do.
- Yeah, I always forget these dos
on the ends of these lines.
So that's just something to keep in mind.
And this hello function is currently returning an atom.
So it's the atom :world and an atom is just a name
whose value is the same as its name or a constant.
Let's just have it return a proper greeting here.
So we'll use an Elixir string,
which is double quotes, no surprise.
And then, we can use string interpolation.
If we wanted to say hello, some name
and then we could pass that name
in as an argument to the hello function.
Then to call a function, we're going to
come down outside of this module and I'm
going to use IO, that's a module name that's built into
Elixir, use puts, and then we use the module name,
which is servy in this case and the name of the
function hello, and then we'll just pass it Elixir.
So defining modules and functions and
then calling those functions on the modules
is pretty straightforward.
Obviously, the next thing we
want to do is to run our code.
And to do that we're going to need to compile our
Elixir files to bytecode and then run that bytecode
on the Erlang virtual machine.
Now the Erlang virtual machine is like 20 years old,
so you can imagine what we're going to have to go
through just to print out Hello, Elixir to the console.
Makefiles, cross-compilers.
- The good news is once we get past
this point, it's all downhill from here.
Just kidding.
Elixir makes it really easy to run our code.
- So the first way to run an Elixir file is using the
elixir command and our servy.ex file is down in the
lib directory, so I just give it the relative path
there and we see we get Hello, Elixir, no surprise.
But this is pretty cool when you think about it because
the file got compiled in memory into bytecode and then
it was run on the Erlang virtual machine.
Now our file lives in the mix project directory under
lib, but you can create a one-off Elixir file anywhere
you want and run it using the elixir command.
It doesn't have to be in a mix project directory like
we have it here, but unless it's a one-off file,
I always put my code in a mix project directory because
I usually end up with multiple files and that's just
the proper way to do it.
I can also run this back in Sublime.
I've got it set up if I do Apple + B,
I get the output there.
It's Hello, Elixir.
And this is just set up to run the Elixir
command on the current file.
And I'm going to use this approach at
least for the first part of the course,
just so you don't have to watch me switch back and
forth between the command line and the editor.
And it's just an easy way to get the results quickly.
- Another way to run our app is to
use Elixir's interactive shell IEx.
- So you type iex just like that and it'll
evaluate any expression, no surprise.
You can also call any built-in modules like
String and the function reverse, for example.
But what happens if we try our servy module
and call our hello passing in my name?
Well, it says servy.hello is undefined.
The module servy is not available.
And that's because by default IEx
doesn't know about this servy file.
So one way to compile it and load it is using the c
function and then we just give it a string,
which is the relative path to the file we want to run.
And you notice we immediately got Hello, Elixir.
So this compiled the file in memory and then loaded the
servy module into the session and then any code that's
outside of the module is interpreted.
So this code right here that prints
out Hello, Elixir got interpreted,
which is why we see the output right here.
To get out of IEx, you can hit Ctrl + C and
this is going to open up the break menu.
And then you can either type A right here to
get out of this session, or as most people do,
you just hit Ctrl + C again.
So to get off IEx, it's basically two Ctrl + Cs.
There's a shortcut to starting IEx and loading up a
file. You can just use IEx and then give it the name
of the file, a relative path again as an argument.
And again, the file is compiled in memory and
the servy module is loaded into the runtime.
And then, any code that's outside of the module is
interpreted, which is why we see this right here.
So that's a shortcut to opening IEx and then using
the c function to compile it and to get out of this,
I'm just going to hit Ctrl + C twice.
One final way to run code in IEx is to start the IEx
session with a -S option and then mix,
and then it says it compiled the file.
We got the output because it
interpreted this line up here again.
When you start IEx with the -S mix
option, it knows about the project.
So we're in an IEx session
in the context of our application.
So we can go ahead and use our
module Servy.hello, for example.
I tend to use this approach because it compiles
and loads all the modules in the project,
and we can interact with any of the application
code so you don't have to compile it or load IEx
with a specific file.
You've got access to everything you need right here.
- So let's look at what happens
when we need to recompile.
Let's say we change our code from Hello to Howdy.
- Well, if I save that away here in Sublime, I can
hit Apple + B, again, we get back, Howdy, Elixir!
Down here, If I'm still in an IEx session, I can use
the r function and then give it the name of a module.
In this case, our module is Servy, and that
recompiles and reloads the given module.
You see we get a little bit of warning here saying,
we're redefining that module and then it recompiled,
reloaded it, and we see that we've got Howdy,
Elixir! Because it interpreted that line again.
So now if we say hello("mike"), it says Howdy, mike!
So I'm going to go ahead and comment out this line
right here so it doesn't get interpreted every time we
load up our project in IEx going forward.
- So now we have a project and a jumping-off
point from which to build our web server.
Next up, we'll handle our first HTTP request.